NICOLÒ DAL FABBRO

n.dalfabbro@gmail.com https://ndf96.github.io Philadelphia, PA, USA

Ph.D. in Information and Communication Technology. Currently a postdoctoral researcher at the University of Pennsylvania, USA. My research interest is mainly in the analysis and design of multi-agent and distributed machine learning algorithms, with a focus on wireless communications and sensing.

EDUCATION

PHD, INFORMATION AND COMMUNICATION TECHNOLOGY:

Thesis: Pushing the Boundaries of Federated Learning: Super-Linear Convergence and Reinforcement Learning Over Wireless Department of Information Engineering, University of Padova, Italy | October 2020 - October 2023

VISITING PHD STUDENT, GRASP (General Robotics, Automation, Sensing, and Perception)

Electrical and Systems Engineernig, University of Pennsylvania, USA | September 2022 - April 2023

M. S., TELECOMMUNICATIONS ENGINEERING

Thesis: WiFi-based human sensing

Department of Information Engineering, University of Padova, Italy | 2018 - 2020

EXCHANGE STUDENT, Swiss European Mobility Program (SEMP) (Scholarship Recipient)

École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL), School of Computer and Communication Sciences, Switzerland | 2019 - 2020

B. S. IN INFORMATION ENGINEERING

University of Padova, Italy | 2015 - 2018

WORK EXPERIENCE

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Electrical and Systems Engineering, University of Pennsylvania, USA | November 2023 - Current

• Conducting research in Federated Learning and Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning with applications in autonomous driving and underwater robotics.

UNIVERSITY RESEARCH ASSISTANT

University of Padova, Padova, Italy | September 2020 – September 2023

• Research on algorithm design for Federated Learning in the context of wireless 5G/6G networks, theoretical analysis of distributed and multi-agent reinforcement learning algorithms.

UNIVERSITY TEACHING ASSISTANT, Numerical Calculus

Department of Mathematics, University of Padova, Italy | February 2022 - July 2022

• Conducting practical sessions with excercises on numerical calculus in Matlab

RESEARCH INTERN, SIGNET RESEARCH GROUP, DEI

University of Padova, Italy | February 2020 - August 2020

• Experimental research on WiFi-based human sensing

SKILLS

Programming Languages and Software

Python | MATLAB | C++ | LaTeX | Linux | Github | Slack

Multilingual

Italian (native) | English (fluent) | French (basic)

AWARDS AND FELLOWSHIPS

- Best PhD Thesis Award by the Italian Telecommunications and Information Technology Group (GTTI) for the year 2024: http://www.gtti.it/awards
- Winner of the Fall 2022 IEEE DataPort Dataset Upload Contest in the Machine Learning category based on unique dataset views as measured by Google Analytics and a review from a committee of the IEEE (https://ieee-dataport.org/documents/csi-dataset-wireless-human-sensing-80-mhz-wi-fi-channels)
- Al x Science fellow (2024-current), University of Pennsylvania data science postdoctoral fellowship (5K USD yearly research fund): https://web.sas.upenn.edu/data-science/postdoctoral-fellows/

PUBLICATIONS

Luca Ballotta, Nicolò Dal Fabbro, Giovanni Perin, Luca Schenato, Michele Rossi, Giuseppe Piro. **VREM-FL: Mobility-Aware Computation-Scheduling Co-Design for Vehicular Federated Learning**, *IEEE Transactions on Vehicular Technology*, 2024, doi: https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/10715716

Nicolò Dal Fabbro, Arman Adibi, Aritra Mitra, George J. Pappas. **DASA: Delay-Adaptive Multi-Agent Stochastic Approximation**, Accepted for publication, 62nd IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC), 2024

Arman Adibi, Nicolò Dal Fabbro, Luca Schenato, Sanjeev Kulkarni, H. Vincent Poor, George J. Pappas, Hamed Hassani and Aritra Mitra. **Stochastic Approximation with Delayed Updates: Finite-Time Rates under Markovian Sampling**, The 27th International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS), Valencia, Spain, 2024, https://proceedings.mlr.press/v238/adibi24a/

Nicolò Dal Fabbro, Arman Adibi, Aritra Mitra, George J. Pappas. **Finite-Time Analysis of Asynchronous Multi-Agent TD Learning**, *The 2024 American Control Conference (ACC)*, 2024

N. Dal Fabbro, S. Dey, M. Rossi, and L. Schenato. **SHED: A Newton-Type Algorithm for Federated Learning based on Incremental Hessian Eigenvector Sharing.** *Automatica*, 2024, doi: 10.1016/j.automatica.2023.111460

Andrea Agiollo, Enkeleda Bardhi, Mauro Conti, Nicolò Dal Fabbro, Riccardo Lazzeretti. **Anonymous Federated Learning via Named-Data Networking**, *Future Generation Computer Systems*, 2024, doi: 10.1016/j.future.2023.11.009

N. Dal Fabbro, A. Mitra, and G. J. Pappas. **Federated TD Learning over Finite-Rate Erasure Channels: Linear Speedup under Markovian Sampling.** *IEEE Control Systems Letters*, 2023 doi: 10.1109/LCSYS.2023.3287499 (also accepted and presented at the 62nd IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC 2023)

F. Meneghello, N. Dal Fabbro, D. Garlisi, I. Tinnirello, and M. Rossi. **A CSI Dataset for Wireless Human Sensing on 80 MHz Wi-Fi Channels**. *IEEE Communications Magazine*, 2023, doi: 10.1109/MCOM.005.2200720

N. Dal Fabbro, M. Rossi, L. Schenato, and S. Dey. **Q-SHED: Distributed Optimization at the Edge via Hessian Eigenvectors Quantization.** *IEEE International Conference on Communications (ICC)*, Rome, Italy, 2023, doi: 10.1109/ICC45041.2023.10279510

N. Dal Fabbro, A. Mitra, R. W. Heath, L. Schenato, and G. J. Pappas. **Over-the-Air Federated TD Learning**. *Sixth Conference on Machine Learning and Systems (MLSys23)*, Workshop on Resource-Constrained Learning in Wireless Networks, Miami, Florida, 2023

F. Meneghello, D. Garlisi, N. Dal Fabbro, I. Tinnirello, and M. Rossi. **SHARP: Environment and Person Independent Activity Recognition with Commodity IEEE 802.11 Access Points**. *IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing*, 2022, doi: 10.1109/TMC.2022.3185681

N. Dal Fabbro, M. Rossi, G. Pillonetto, L. Schenato, and G. Piro. **Model-Free Radio Map Estimation in Massive MIMO Systems via Semi-Parametric Gaussian Regression.** *IEEE Wireless Communications Letters*, 2022, doi: 10.1109/LWC.2021.3132458

ADDITIONAL EXPERIENCE AND VOLUNTEERING

- Organizing weekly meetings between group members of Prof. George Pappas research group at the University of Pennsylvania. I have been organizing the meetings with the main objective of spurring collaboration, stimulating knowledge exchange and networking
- Attended and actively contributed to prestigious international PhD schools, including the IEEE/DEI Summer PhD School of Information Engineering "Silvano Pupolin" – SSIE 2022 (https://ssie.dei.unipd.it/), and the 5G International PhD School, December 2020 (https://www.5gitaly.eu/2020/)
- Reviewer for esteemed international journals, such as Signal Processing (Elsevier), Automatica (Elsevier), Transactions on Mobile Computing (IEEE), Transactions on Vehicular Technology (IEEE) since 2021
- Co-founded and actively participated in Venice Calls (https://www.venicecalls.com/), a non-profit organization of social promotion in Venice. Helped coordinate volunteers during the 2019 flooding crisis, providing assistance to affected citizens, institutions, and businesses (https://www.festivalitaca.net/2020/02/venice-calls-gli-angeli-veneziani-dellacqua-alta/). Organized public events, including conferences and clean-up initiatives in the Venice Lagoon. Contributed to promoting public participation and cultural events.